<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemata/cgrid.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemata/cgrid.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Beethoven, Weber and Berlioz</title>
            <title type="sub">Imitation and influence</title>
            <author>
               <name><forename>John</forename> <surname>Warrack</surname></name>
               <email/>
               <affiliation>was formerly Lecturer in Music at Oxford University. In youth he played the oboe professionally and later became chief music critic of the London <hi rend="italic">Sunday Telegraph</hi>. His books include a history of German opera and a study of the life and works of Weber, who has remained at the centre of his studies on German Romantic opera. He has published many articles on the subject and edited Weber&#x2019;s First Piano Concerto for the Sämtliche Werke, and has made performing translations of many operas. He is a member of the Beirat of the Internationale Weber Gesellschaft.</affiliation>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Virtueller Forschungsverbund Edirom (ViFE)</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers001">
                  <p>Bach, Johann Sebastian</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers002">
                  <p>Beethoven, Ludwig van</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work003"><hi rend="italic">Sinfonie</hi> Nr.&#8239;3 Es-Dur op.&#8239;55</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work005"><hi rend="italic">Sinfonie</hi> Nr.&#8239;5 c-Moll op.&#8239;67</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work007"><hi rend="italic">Sinfonie</hi> Nr.&#8239;7 A-Dur op.&#8239;92</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work008"><hi rend="italic">Sinfonie</hi> Nr.&#8239;8 F-Dur op.&#8239;93</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work009"><hi rend="italic">Sinfonie</hi> Nr.&#8239;9 d-Moll op.&#8239;125</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work001"><hi rend="italic">Fidelio</hi></p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers004">
                  <p>Bennet, Toussaint</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers005">
                  <p>Berlioz, Hector</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work022"><hi rend="italic">Harold en Italie</hi></p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work023"><hi rend="italic">Symphonie fantastique</hi></p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work024"><hi rend="italic">La damnation de Faust</hi></p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work025"><hi rend="italic">La Captive</hi></p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work026"><hi rend="italic">Huit Scènes de Faust</hi></p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work027"><hi rend="italic">Les francs-juges</hi></p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work028"><hi rend="italic">Grande Symphonie funèbre et triomphale</hi></p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work029"><hi rend="italic">Roméo et Juliette</hi></p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers006">
                  <p>Berlioz, Nanci</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers008">
                  <p>Bloom, Peter</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers009">
                  <p>Boieldieu, François Adrien</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers010">
                  <p>Byron, George Gordon</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers011">
                  <p>Cairns, David</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers013">
                  <p>Castil-Blaze, François Henri Joseph</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers014">
                  <p>Catel, Charles Simon</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers015">
                  <p>Cherubini, Luigi</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers016">
                  <p>Dalayrac, Nicolas</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers017">
                  <p>Debussy, Claude</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work060"><hi rend="italic">Pelléas et Mélisande</hi></p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers018">
                  <p>Ferrand, Humbert</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers019">
                  <p>Gardiner, John Eliot</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers020">
                  <p>Godet, Robert</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers021">
                  <p>Habeneck, François-Antoine</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers023">
                  <p>Haydn, Joseph</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers025">
                  <p>Händel, Georg Friedrich</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers026">
                  <p>Isouard, Niccolò</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers027">
                  <p>Lami, Eugène</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers028">
                  <p>Liszt, Franz</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers030">
                  <p>Mahler, Gustav</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers031">
                  <p>Mendelssohn Bartholdy, Felix</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers032">
                  <p>Moore, Thomas</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers033">
                  <p>Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers034">
                  <p>Murphy, Kerry</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers036">
                  <p>Méhul, Étienne Nicolas</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work050"><hi rend="italic">Uthal</hi></p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work051"><hi rend="italic">Ariodant</hi></p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers037">
                  <p>Reeve, Katherine</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers038">
                  <p>Rocher, Édouard</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers039">
                  <p>Sauvage, Thomas</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers041">
                  <p>Schubert, Franz</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work040"><hi rend="italic">Gretchen am Spinnrade</hi>, D&#8239;118</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work041"><hi rend="italic">Sonate</hi> A-Dur, D&#8239;959</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers043">
                  <p>Shakespeare, William</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers044">
                  <p>Spontini, Gaspare</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers045">
                  <p>Tschaikowski, Pjotr Iljitsch</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers046">
                  <p>Vernet, Horace</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers047">
                  <p>Wagner, Richard</p>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="warrack-pers048">
                  <p>Weber, Carl Maria von</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz</hi>, WeV C.7</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work011"><hi rend="italic">Oberon</hi>, WeV C.10</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work012"><hi rend="italic">Euryanthe</hi>, WeV C.9</p>
                  <p n="work" xml:id="warrack-work013"><hi rend="italic">Aufforderung zum Tanz</hi>, WeV S.10</p>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2015-11-04T13:32:00"
            who="https://github.com/peterstadler">Für erste Durchsicht durch den Autor vorbereitet.</change>
         <change when="2015-07-31T16:52:02.033+02:00"
            who="https://github.com/peterstadler">Text bearbeitet, Personen, Literatur und Werke ausgezeichnet.</change>
         <change when="2015-06-05T23:26:02.033+02:00"
            who="https://github.com/peterstadler">Initial transformation from OxGarage TEI P5 to jTEI customization.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="warrack-abstract"><p>Berlioz&#x2019;a admiration for German music took the form of both critical argument and creative influence on his own music. The two German composers representing all that he most admired were Beethoven and Weber. John Warrack suggests some of the important influences they had on Berlioz&#x2019;s own music, but also, by reference to his critical writings, his journalism (especially in the Paris <hi rend="italic">Journal des débats</hi>) and his correspondence, shows how he powerfully argued their case to his sometimes reluctant countrymen.</p></div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Readers of the <hi rend="italic">Gazette Musicale de Paris</hi> on the Sunday morning of the 6th of July 1834 must have been surprised by the anonymous leading article that met their gaze. <q>The numerous admirers of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> and <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> are overjoyed</q>, it began. <q>Authorization for the performance of German opera has just been granted to the Théâtre Ventadour</q>, adding that this was a matter of not just a few performances but the annual engagement of a German company. The writer went on to lambast the poverty and triviality of the Parisian musical theatre, and to declare that, <q>The German theatre coming to us from beyond the Rhine, without making any concession to the stupid demands of  our Parisian fashions […] will with its vigorous harmonies, its original melodies, its abrupt forms, such varied and original orchestration, its spirited choruses, its blonde and dreamy prima donnas certainly make a sharp contrast to our national habits</q>; and he looks forward to a new inquisitive and enthusiastic audience invading the Ventadour unable to resist the force of <q>the Titan <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name></q>.<note xml:id="warrack-ftn1" n="1"><q>Les nombreux adorateurs de <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> et de <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> sont dans la joie. L’autorisation de jouer l’opéra allemand vient d’être accordée au théâtre Ventadour […]. Le théâtre allemand nous arrivant d’outre-Rhin, sans aucune concession faire aux sottes exigences de nos mode Parisiennes, […] avec ses harmonies pleines de vigueur, ses mélodies originales, ses formes abruptes, son instrumentation si variée, si originale, se chœurs entrainans, ses blondes et rêveuses prime donnes, formera certe un piquant contraste à nos habitudes nationales</q>. <hi rend="italic">Gazette musicale</hi>, 6&#x00A0;July 1834, pp.&#8239;213&#x2013;14.</note>
            The article is unsigned; but are we beginning to suspect who the author might be? <name ref="#warrack-pers037">Katherine Reeve</name> and <name ref="#warrack-pers034">Kerry Murphy</name> have attributed it to <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name>;<note><ref target="#Holoman1987" type="bibl">p.&#8239;438, col.&#8239;2, C&#x00A0;64</ref>. <hi rend="italic">De l&#x2019;utilité d&#x2019;un Opéra-Allemand à Paris</hi>.</note> and the verve of the writing and the vigour of the attack on Parisian manners lend force to that, but the real give-away is in the opening sentence connecting <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> and <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>. When he wrote about German music, <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> repeatedly linked their names; indeed, turning the pages of the early volumes of his letters in the Collected Edition, one finds their names more often paired than mentioned separately. And in <hi rend="italic">Le Correspondant</hi>  he writes in 1830, <quote source="#warrack-ftn3">In the compositions of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> and of <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> one recognises a poetic thought revealing itself everywhere. It is music depending entirely on itself, without the help of words to determine its expression; its language therefore becomes extremely vague and thereby acquires even greater power for those who are gifted with imagination […] Hence the extraordinary effects, the strange sensations, the inexpressible emotions produced by the symphonies, the quartets, overtures, sonatas of <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> and of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name>.</quote><note xml:id="warrack-ftn3" n="3" type="bibl"><q>[…] dans les compositions de <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> et de <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>, on reconnaît une pensée poétique qui se manifeste partout. C’est la musique livrée à elle-même, sans le secours de la parole pour en préciser l’expression; son langage devient alors extrêmement vague et par là  même acquiert encore plus de puissance sur les êtres doués d’imagination […] De là les effets extraordinaires, les sensations étranges, les émotions inexprimables que produisent les symphonies, les quatuors, ouvertures, sonates de <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> et de <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name></q>. <hi rend="italic">Le Correspondant</hi>, 22&#x00A0;October 1830.</note>
         </p>
         <p>On the face of it, this may seem rather an uneven choice of composers to represent the great tradition of German music. Moreover, <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> wrote no string quartets, and <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> certainly did not rank <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> two youthful symphonies with any of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name>. But we must remember, perhaps reluctantly, that for much of his life <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> considered <name ref="#warrack-pers001">Bach</name> an old fogey, dismissing his fugues as <q>gibberish</q>,<note xml:id="warrack-ftn4" n="4"><q>j’abhorre ce grimoire</q>. Letter to <name ref="#warrack-pers006">Nanci Berlioz</name>, 28&#x00A0;December 1829, <ref type="bibl" target="#BerliozCorrespI">p.&#8239;294</ref>.</note> and called <name ref="#warrack-pers025">Handel</name> <q>a barrel of pork and beer</q>;<note xml:id="warrack-ftn5" n="5"><q>[…] la lourde face <hi rend="italic">emperruqué</hi> de ce tonneau de porc et de bière qu’on nomme <name ref="#warrack-pers025">Händel</name>!</q> Letter to <name ref="#warrack-pers004">Toussaint Bennet</name>, 26 or 27&#x00A0;January 1857, <!--<hi rend="italic">CG</hi> V (1855&#x2013;59), (Paris, 1989), --><ref target="#BerliozCorrespV" type="bibl">p.&#8239;418</ref>.</note>
            he was selective in his appreciation of <name ref="#warrack-pers033">Mozart</name>, which only grew slowly, and he could be surprisingly disdainful of <name ref="#warrack-pers023">Haydn</name>, especially when there was any question of comparing the two of them with <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name>, whom he held in awe; while he felt an affinity amounting to personal closeness to <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>, whom, in the story he tells so entertainingly in the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, he vainly pursued round Paris in 1826 in the hope of a meeting. Almost all composers, even ones like <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> with sharp intelligences and equally sharp pens, form their judgements with reference to their creative needs, and it seems that he felt he needed to clear the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century field so as make way for 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century advances.</p>
         <p>When <name ref="#warrack-pers021">Habeneck</name> introduced <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> into the newly founded Conservatoire concerts, the <title ref="#warrack-work003"><hi rend="italic">Eroica</hi></title> on 9th March 1828, the <title ref="#warrack-work005">Fifth Symphony</title> on 13th April, <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> wrote, <quote source="#warrack-ftn6">I had just had the successive revelations of <name ref="#warrack-pers043">Shakespeare</name> and <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>. Now, at another point on the horizon I saw the giant form of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> rear up. The shock was almost as great as that of <name ref="#warrack-pers043">Shakespeare</name> had been. <pb/><name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> opened before me a new world of music, as <name ref="#warrack-pers043">Shakespeare</name> had revealed a new universe of poetry.</quote><note xml:id="warrack-ftn6" n="6" type="bibl"><!--<hi rend="italic">Hector Berlioz: Mémoires</hi>, présentée et annotée Pierre Citron (Paris, 1991), --><ref type="bibl" target="#BerliozMemoiresFR">Ch.&#8239;20</ref>, trans. <ref target="#BerliozMemoiresEN" type="bibl"/><!--<hi rend="italic">The Memoirs of Hector Berlioz</hi>, ed. David Cairns (London, 1969)-->.</note> 
            As all Berliozians know, he wrote copiously and eloquently about <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name>, and it’s still rewarding to read the accounts of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> symphonies that found their way into the collection <hi rend="italic">A travers chants</hi>. Descriptive writing of this kind is out of favour nowadays; but how revealing much of it is, and how sympathetic to find a commentator willing to confess himself puzzled, as with the <hi rend="italic">Allegretto scherzando</hi> of the <title ref="#warrack-work008">Eighth Symphony</title>. I’m sure I’m not the only listener to have been bewildered on first hearing that movement’s abrupt ending, and to remain so, as <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> seems suddenly to lose patience with what he’s doing and just scribbles a violent <hi rend="italic">fortissimo</hi> across the page as if saying, <q>Oh, forget it</q>. 
            Turn to <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> for enlightenment, and we find that he can’t explain it to himself either: <q>Je n’ai jamais pu m’expliquer cette boutade</q> &#x2013; <hi rend="italic">boutade</hi> is a wonderful word meaning a sudden illogical outburst, often of bad temper; and it perfectly catches <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> occasional propensity to shake his fist or burst out with a sudden laugh in the face of his audience. If we turn back to the title page of <hi rend="italic">A travers chants</hi>, we find that <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> describes his collection of essays as <q>Études musicales, adorations, boutades et critiques</q>.</p>
         <p>But it’s not my intention to offer another discussion of <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz’s</name> writing on <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name>. We already have <name ref="#warrack-pers011">David Cairns’s</name> admirable essay on the subject in <name ref="#warrack-pers008">Peter Bloom’s</name> <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Companion</hi>.<ref xml:id="warrack-ftn7" n="7" type="bibl" target="#Cairns2000"/> I would prefer to consider some of the ways in which <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz’s</name> own music was influenced. And as a preliminary, perhaps we ought to be clear what we really mean by the often loosely applied term, <q>influence</q>. There is certain to be argument about where the bounds lie. We should surely refer to more than plain imitation, just copying a gesture perhaps in a slightly different way, and mean what the word literally implies, the flowing, <hi rend="italic">Einfluss</hi>, of an idea from the creative imagination of one artist into that of another. The opening of the finale of <title ref="#warrack-work022"><hi rend="italic">Harold in Italy</hi></title> is surely more imitation than influence. <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> had read through <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> <title ref="#warrack-work009">Ninth Symphony</title> in 1829 but not actually heard the work until January 1834, the month in which he began work on <title ref="#warrack-work022"><hi rend="italic">Harold</hi></title>. I venture to suggest that the opening of the finale with quotations of the three previous movements is the plain use of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> idea, the impact of which was fresh in his mind and which solved a problem for him, but is something that has not been fully absorbed into his imagination. He had also heard the <title ref="#warrack-work007">Seventh Symphony</title>, performed twice at Habeneck’s Conservatoire concerts in 1829, and the effect of the <hi rend="italic">Allegretto</hi> on the audience was captured in the picture by <name ref="#warrack-pers046">Horace Vernet’s</name> pupil <name ref="#warrack-pers027">Eugène Lami</name> of members of an enrapt audience, smiling, frowning in concentration, lips pursed, mouth open, head in hands, totally absorbed by the music. </p>
         <p><name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz’s</name> critical reaction was one of his most detailed and poetic descriptions, poetic indeed to the point of including two <name ref="#warrack-pers043">Shakespeare</name> quotations and one misquotation from <name ref="#warrack-pers032">Thomas Moore</name>. Surely this plunged more deeply into his imagination, bringing into his mind something not from <name ref="#warrack-pers010">Byron</name>, the ostensible source of his symphony, but from his distant memory of lying in a field as a boy and listening to the chanting of a passing Rogation procession across the stirring of the corn. Describing <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> movement, he writes of the insistent rhythm of dactyl and spondee (&#x2013;&#8239;.&#8239;.&#8239;|&#8239;&#x2013;&#8239;&#x2013;) and of the skill with which <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> varies his expression of this inexorable rhythm. His own <title ref="#warrack-work022">Pilgrims’ March</title> with them singing the evening prayer suggests the endless repetition of a chant; but in fact, though as with <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name>, the rhythm does not change, the melody changes the whole time, and if we take just the first ten repetitions, at the end of each eight bar phrase the varied melody ends with a different cadence and comes to rest on a different chord.</p>
         <p>Surely one could say that whereas the <title ref="#warrack-work022"><hi rend="italic">Harold</hi></title> finale’s recollections are the re-use of a <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> device, <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> <title ref="#warrack-work007"><hi rend="italic">Allegretto</hi></title> inspired something deep in <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz’s</name> own imagination, that this is indeed influence rather than imitation. There are of course other examples one could cite. There is for instance the broken melody, which <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> must have noticed in <name ref="#warrack-pers023">Haydn’s</name> generally witty uses, but which he himself employed to strong dramatic effect.  Of a number of examples in <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name>, the most moving is surely the end of the <title ref="#warrack-work003">Funeral March</title> of the <title ref="#warrack-work003">Eroica</title>, where the music several times breaks off as if too burdened by grief to continue. Certainly it moved <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name>, who admits as much and concentrates on it in his essay. With his Virgilian sensibilities, he compares the movement to one of the most emotionally charged passages in the whole of the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>, the funeral cortège of the young Pallas that opens Book Eleven; he just quotes a few lines, and saves his detailed description for the fragmentation of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> march theme. Other composers have turned to this device of the broken melody, memorably <name ref="#warrack-pers041">Schubert</name> at the climax of <title ref="#warrack-work040"><q>Gretchen am Spinnrade</q></title>, when Gretchen is too overcome by the thought of Faust’s kiss to be able to continue and both her voice and the spinning wheel come to a halt. Again, in the finale of <name ref="#warrack-pers041">Schubert’s</name> late <title ref="#warrack-work041">A major piano sonata</title>, when the great striding melody falters and stumbles heart-breakingly to a halt several times before gathering itself together for the conclusion. <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name>, no pianist, may not have known the sonata, but he turns the device of the broken melody that moved him in the <title ref="#warrack-work003"><hi rend="italic">Eroica</hi></title> to his own ends in <title ref="#warrack-work024"><hi rend="italic">Faust</hi></title> with <q>D’amour, l’ardente flame</q> and at the affecting end of <title ref="#warrack-work025"><hi rend="italic">La Captive</hi></title>.
         </p>
         <pb/>
         <p>Most significantly, <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> was, famously, one of the composers who recognized that with the <title ref="#warrack-work009">Ninth Symphony</title>, <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name>, this great German composer, had brought music to a critical point. Symphonic music could never be the same again. For <name ref="#warrack-pers047">Wagner</name>, claiming that the <title ref="#warrack-work009">Ninth Symphony</title> was music crying out for redemption by poetry and, with his short story <hi rend="italic">Eine Pilgerfahrt zu Beethoven</hi> in 1840, that the Master’s cloak had fallen upon him, the symphonization of drama was the answer; and to make his point it was with the <title ref="#warrack-work009">Ninth Symphony</title> that he opened Bayreuth in 1876. <name ref="#warrack-pers028">Liszt</name>, though humble before <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> genius, writes one scholar, <quote source="#warrack-ftn8">considered his orchestral compositions to be a continuation of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven’s</name> achievement. According to the view strongly held by <name ref="#warrack-pers028">Liszt</name> and <name ref="#warrack-pers047">Wagner</name>, the symphony &#x2013; with the exception of Berlioz &#x2013; had become stagnant after Beethoven. Liszt saw it as his mission to take orchestral composition further along the path initiated by the great symphonist.</quote><ref target="#Shulstad2005" type="bibl" xml:id="warrack-ftn8" n="8"/>
            
            As for <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> himself, as he wrote to his chemist friend <name ref="#warrack-pers038">Édouard Rocher</name> in 1829, <quote source="#warrack-ftn9">What musical ideas are fermenting in me […]   Now that I have burst the bridle of routine, I see a vast field spreading out before me, one which scholastic rules were forbidding me to enter. Now that I have heard this awe-inspiring giant <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> I understand the point which the art of music has reached; it’s a matter of taking it up at that point and pressing on further […] not further, that’s impossible, he’s reached the limits of art, but as far in another direction.</quote><note xml:id="warrack-ftn9" n="9" type="bibl"><q>que d’idées musicales fermentent en moi […]  à présent que j’ai brisé le frein de la routine, je vois se dérouler un champ immense, dans lequel les règles scholastiques me défendaient d’entrer. A présent que j’ai entendu cet effrayant géant Beethoven, je sais à quel point en est l’art musical, il s’agit de le prendre à ce point-là et de pousser plus loin […]  pas plus loin, c’est impossible, il a atteint les bornes de l’art, mais aussi loin dans une autre route.</q> Letter to Édouard Rocher, 11 January 1829, <!--<hi rend="italic">CG</hi> I (1803&#x2013;1832), Paris 1972, --><ref target="#BerliozCorrespI" type="bibl">p.&#8239;229</ref>.</note> 
            And so the new direction was dramatic symphony, the <title ref="#warrack-work023"><hi rend="italic">Symphonie fantastique</hi></title>, <title ref="#warrack-work022"><hi rend="italic">Harold in Italy</hi></title>, the <title ref="#warrack-work028"><hi rend="italic">Symphonie funèbre et triomphale</hi></title>, especially the symphonically subtle <title ref="#warrack-work029"><hi rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</hi></title>.</p>
         <p><name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> and <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> met only once, in 1823 when <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> was in Vienna for the première of <title ref="#warrack-work012"><hi rend="italic">Euryanthe</hi></title>. With a couple of friends he drove out to Baden, where the two composers greeted each other warmly and went out for a convivial lunch together at which <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> played a generous and attentive host. <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> had a particular admiration for <title ref="#warrack-work001"><hi rend="italic">Fidelio</hi></title>, which he had conducted in Dresden, and <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> in turn was very impressed with <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz</hi></title>, which by then had embarked on its triumphant progress round Europe. It reached Paris in the following year, at the Odéon on Thursday the 7th of December 1824 in the guise of <hi rend="italic">Robin des bois</hi>, adapted by <name ref="#warrack-pers039">Thomas Sauvage</name> and the ubiquitous <name ref="#warrack-pers013">Castil-Blaze</name> but apparently suffering only the elimination of the Hermit. The anonymous reviewer in the <hi rend="italic">Journal des débats</hi> treated the music with respect and praised the orchestra, but was scathing about the feebleness of singers, declaring that confiding <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> score to them was <quote source="#warrack-ftn10">like giving the armour of Achilles to pygmies</quote>.<note xml:id="warrack-ftn10" n="10" type="bibl"><q>C’étoit remettre à les pygmées les armes d’Achille</q>. <hi rend="italic">Journal des débats</hi>, Thursday 9&#x00A0;December 1824, Cols 1&#x2013;4.</note> 
            A second performance which he mentioned as planned for the following Tuesday appears to have been cancelled, but nine days later the work returned, it seems further adapted by <name ref="#warrack-pers039">Sauvage</name> and <name ref="#warrack-pers013">Castil-Blaze</name>. However mutilated, it was very popular, receiving over a hundred performances. As <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> notes bitterly, in his sharp account of the première which opens Chapter&#x00A0;16 of the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, it made the Odéon a fortune, and <name ref="#warrack-pers013">Castil-Blaze</name> a good hundred thousand francs. </p>
         <p>In his English translation, <name ref="#warrack-pers011">David Cairns</name> footnotes the butchery inflicted upon the work; but rather than dwell on that, we may note that <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> claims to have abandoned his worship of classical opera and forsaken the Opéra, never missing a performance at the Odéon, soon knowing <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz</hi></title>, or what was performed of it, by heart. Between 1825 and 1827 he was largely occupied with his first opera, <title ref="#warrack-work027"><hi rend="italic">Les Francs-juges</hi></title>, whose tribulations have been well documented; but we should note here the letter he wrote to the work’s librettist, his friend <name ref="#warrack-pers018">Humbert Ferrand</name>, in June 1829, when the work was rejected by the Opéra and he was entertaining hopes of German performance. He writes, <q>I’ll have it translated into German. I’ll finish the music; I’ll make it an opera like the <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Freischütz</hi></title>, half spoken, half melodrama, and the rest music, I’ll add four or five pieces […]</q><note xml:id="warrack-ftn11" n="11"><q>Je vais me le faire traduire en allemand. J’achèverai la musique; j’en ferai un opéra comme le <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Freischütz</hi></title>, moitié parlé, moitié mélodrame, et le reste musique, j’ajouterai quartre or cinq morceaux […]</q> <!--<hi rend="italic">CG</hi> I (1803&#x2013;32), Paris 1972, --><ref type="bibl" target="#BerliozCorrespI">p.&#8239;256</ref>.</note> 
            When he writes of the work being like <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz</hi></title>, he is evidently referring principally to the form. In the overture and the surviving pieces of <title ref="#warrack-work027"><hi rend="italic">Les Francs-juges</hi></title>, there is not much specifically Weberian. Perhaps one could single out one use of clarinets in the low chalumeau register, some piccolo flashes, a certain independence for the violas; though these are characteristic of <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> scoring, they might not strike one if one were not on the lookout for them. The two composers were close. As is well known, when <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz</hi></title> was finally to be admitted through the sacred portals of the Opéra he agreed to write the compulsory recitatives, reluctantly and largely so as prevent anyone with less affinity to <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> from making a hash of it. And of course, he also orchestrated <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> <title ref="#warrack-work013"><hi rend="italic">Invitation to the Dance</hi></title> for the compulsory ballet, most brilliantly and Weberishly, too, so much so that it has come to overshadow the work’s essential nature as a virtuoso piano piece. We have come to know the French version of the opera a little better, through publication in the New Berlioz Edition, recordings and also perhaps through performances in Paris and elsewhere by <name ref="#warrack-pers019">John Eliot Gardiner</name>, who has suggested that this is an affinity closer than the work’s anticipations of <name ref="#warrack-pers047">Wagner</name>. Recitative does not tend to be creatively very revealing, but we may note perhaps two points. One is that <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name>, notwithstanding the Opéra’s ban on spoken dialogue, insists on keeping <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> distinction with Caspar singing, that is preserving human expression however deep he is in sin, whereas the devil Samiel, locked in damnation, is bereft of the humanising quality of music. Later, to introduce Aennchen, Agathe’s brightly innocent companion, <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> prepares the way by turning her chatter into some fresh and expressive recitative which might well be by <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>.</p>
         <p>There are indeed <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> influences on <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name>. In some cases, these are coming home to roost, as it were, for <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> based a crucial part of his mature operatic style on French opera. In the years when he was directing the opera at Prague, between 1813 and 1816, then at Dresden until his death in 1826, he consciously built his repertory on French opera as fertilization for the growth of German Romantic opera. The works he introduced to German audiences and musicians include a generous amount of <name ref="#warrack-pers036">Méhul</name>, also works by <name ref="#warrack-pers016">Dalayrac</name>, <name ref="#warrack-pers026">Isouard</name>, <name ref="#warrack-pers009">Boieldieu</name>, <name ref="#warrack-pers014">Catel</name> and French operas by <name ref="#warrack-pers015">Cherubini</name> and <name ref="#warrack-pers044">Spontini</name>. <name ref="#warrack-pers036">Méhul</name>, whom <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> admired with some reservations, gave <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> an example for the melodic manner of Max and Agathe in <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz</hi></title>; more, <name ref="#warrack-pers036">Méhul</name> had the ability to give entire operatic scenes, even whole operas, a characteristic orchestral colour. The Ossianic opera <title ref="#warrack-work050"><hi rend="italic">Uthal</hi></title>, set in Scotland, dispenses with violins altogether and its viola-led fogginess portrays the rain and mist which, all foreigners believe, perpetually shroud the northern part of our island. His <title ref="#warrack-work051"><hi rend="italic">Ariodant</hi></title> set the example of a dissonant chord used motivically, as <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> was to do with Samiel’s diminished sevenths; but further, when the plot descends into sinister darkness, so does the orchestration. This and much else in <name ref="#warrack-pers036">Méhul</name> fell upon receptive ears with <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>, most strikingly in <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz</hi></title> with the descent from the sunlit early village scenes into the dark horror of the Wolf’s Glen and back up again into light and restored happiness. This was something that <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> fully acknowledged, even wrote about, and which he used more skilfully and with more resourcefulness and dramatic force than <name ref="#warrack-pers036">Méhul</name>. The example for <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> was this functional use of orchestration, not as colour added to invention but as a crucial element of the invention. Perhaps the most obvious example is in the <title ref="#warrack-work023"><hi rend="italic">Symphonie fantastique</hi></title>, with the <hi rend="italic">Scène aux champs</hi> and the calling and echoing oboe and cor anglais and the murmuring drums, music that has little meaning without the specific instrumentation. But over a greater range, <pb/>the use of instrumental colour as part of the invention was an essential ingredient of Romantic music and Romantic orchestration.</p>
         
         <p>It is not too difficult to find instances where <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> admired and made use of a Weberian tinge of colour, such as with the chalumeau clarinets; but if we are to regard influence as more than imitating but something flowing from one composer’s imagination into another’s, and also inspiring him, literally breathing life into him, it is the use of ideas in a fresh and individual manner that should be of most interest. If there is a single score which most reflects <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz’s</name> admiration of <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>, of whom he wrote critically very little compared to the amount he wrote on <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name>, then I think it would be <title ref="#warrack-work024"><hi rend="italic">The Damnation of Faust</hi></title>. Perhaps that has something to do with elements in common with <title ref="#warrack-work010"><hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz</hi></title>, both works treating of love and innocence threatened by diabolical forces taking command of a foolishly impulsive young man.</p>
         <p><q><name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> work presents us with the best treatise on instrumentation</q>, it has been declared, by none other than <name ref="#warrack-pers017">Claude Debussy</name>. <q>He scrutinizes the soul of each instrument and exposes it with a gentle hand.</q> This is in the course of a fascinating interview with <name ref="#warrack-pers020">Robert Godet</name> given in the interval of a dress rehearsal of <title ref="#warrack-work060"><hi rend="italic">Pelléas et Mélisande</hi></title> in 1902.<note xml:id="warrack-ftn12" n="12">Translated by Godet and reprinted in <hi rend="italic">The Chesterian</hi>, June&#x00A0;1926.</note> 
            One of many felicities to which he draws attention is the writing for the viola, which <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> sometimes uses unmuted when the other strings are muted, for instance in Agathe’s <q>Leise, leise</q> or at the start of the <title ref="#warrack-work011"><hi rend="italic">Oberon</hi></title> overture. This has something to say about the uncertain nature of the contemporary instrument, but <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> does follow <name ref="#warrack-pers033">Mozart</name>, who liked playing the viola and was the first composer really to understand its solo potential, in writing for it as a solo or obbligato instrument. <name ref="#warrack-pers033">Mozart</name> also gave it orchestral prominence and individuality, rescuing viola players from the underdog position they had occupied for so long (and which no doubt gave rise to all those viola jokes). 
            All of this <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> takes up, so that violas open the whole of <title ref="#warrack-work024"><hi rend="italic">Faust</hi></title>, forlornly <hi rend="italic">dolce ed espressivo</hi>; Aennchen’s solo obbligato viola is borrowed, for different effect, by Marguérite for <q>Le Roi de Thulé</q>; violas are divided and muted at the end of Faust’s <q>Merci doux crépuscule</q> and divided elsewhere in the work to add particular viola colour to the string ensemble. This is a long way from the humble harmony-filler common in so much 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century music. Among the woodwind, <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> emancipation of the piccolo for Caspar’s sinister drinking song<note xml:id="warrack-ftn13" n="13"><name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> regarded this <hi rend="italic">ricanement diabolique</hi> (<q><hi rend="italic">devilish sneering</hi></q>) as <hi rend="italic">une des plus heureuses inventions de l’orchestre de <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name></hi> (<q><hi rend="italic">one of Weber’s most felicitous orchestral inventions</hi></q>), see: <!--<hi rend="italic">Grand traité d’instrumentation</hi>, NBE 24, ed. Peter Bloom, --><ref target="#BerliozTraite" type="bibl">p.&#8239;242</ref>.</note> 
            is turned to similar effect when the evil birds flap at Faust’s ride to damnation, but earlier, with great delicacy, no fewer than three piccolos are called into service for the spirits of flame flickering round Marguerite’s house. At the other flute extreme, <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> had listened to the curiously brooding sound of low flute thirds that introduce Agathe’s <q>Leise, leise</q>. For Brander’s ludicrous song of the rat, <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> can call upon the four bassoons that French orchestras could sometimes boast, and of course he had available a cor anglais, which <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> never did. But he must certainly have been grateful for the inspiration of <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> clarinet writing, taken up in <title ref="#warrack-work024"><hi rend="italic">Faust</hi></title> with the deep chalumeau register, but also the addition of E&#8239;flat clarinet and bass clarinet in novel combinations. And <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber’s</name> woodland hunting horns sound again, though it is Faust who is the quarry as they call and challenge from afar so frighteningly, and then, at the moment when he is presented with Mephistopheles’s pact to which he gives his fatal signature, when they hiss malevolently with stopped tone on a minor third. In a miracle of orchestration, the actual guitar that accompanies Mephistopheles’s serenade in the <title ref="#warrack-work026"><hi rend="italic">Eight Scenes from Faust</hi></title> becomes in the <title ref="#warrack-work024"><hi rend="italic">Damnation</hi></title> a rattle of pizzicato far more sinister for being played without the strum of any human hand. And there’s the grimly ironic use of orchestration when, in <q>Voici des roses</q>, the deceptive sweetness of Mephistopheles’s melody is exposed by the snarl of the accompanying cornet and three trombones.</p>
         <p>I think we can fairly say that <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz’s</name> appreciation of <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> and of <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>, not as of equal stature, but as representative German composers, was of crucial historical importance. If he had not responded to <name ref="#warrack-pers002">Beethoven</name> with such perception, the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century programme symphony might have followed a very different course, or dried up completely. In a some cases, the loss might not have been very great, but in the short term it would have included <name ref="#warrack-pers031">Mendelssohn</name>, who had his own debts to <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name>. Coupled with <name ref="#warrack-pers028">Liszt’s</name> appreciation it would have included a number of Russian composers, including <name ref="#warrack-pers045">Tchaikovsky</name>. Another beneficiary was <name ref="#warrack-pers030">Mahler</name>, who wrote sparingly but appreciatively of <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name> and conducted the <title ref="#warrack-work023"><hi rend="italic">Symphonie fantastique</hi></title> in a programme that also included the <title ref="#warrack-work011"><hi rend="italic">Oberon</hi></title> overture in his first season with the Vienna Philharmonic in 1898, and whose own music certainly shows his appreciation. His links to <name ref="#warrack-pers048">Weber</name> were more direct, and needed no help from <name ref="#warrack-pers005">Berlioz</name>. But that, of course, is another story.</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Holoman1987">D. Kern Holoman, <title level="m">Catalogue of the Works of Hector Berlioz</title>, Kassel 1987 (The New Berlioz Edition&#x00A0;25)</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Cairns2000">David Cairns, <title level="a">Berlioz and Beethoven</title>, in: <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Berlioz</title>, ed. by Peter Bloom, Cambridge 2000, p.&#8239;223&#x2013;34</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Shulstad2005">Reeves Shulstad, <title level="a">Liszt’s symphonic poems and symphonies</title>, in:  <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Liszt</title>, ed. by Kenneth Hamilton, Cambridge 2005, p.&#8239;206</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="BerliozCorrespI">Hector Berlioz, <title level="m">Correspondance Générale</title> I (1803&#x2013;1832), ed. by Pierre Citron, Paris 1972<bibl type="short"><title level="m">CG</title>&#x00A0;I</bibl></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="BerliozCorrespV">Hector Berlioz, <title level="m">Correspondance Générale</title> V (1855&#x2013;1859), ed. by Hugh J. Macdonald and François Lesure, Paris 1989</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="BerliozMemoiresFR">Hector Berlioz, <title level="m">Mémoires</title>, ed. by Pierre Citron, Paris 1991</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="BerliozMemoiresEN"><title level="m">The Memoirs of Hector Berlioz</title>, translated and ed. by David Cairns, London 1969</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="BerliozTraite">Hector Berlioz, <title level="m">Grand Traité d’instrumentation et d’orchestration modernes</title>, ed. by Peter Bloom, Kassel 2003 (The New Berlioz Edition&#x00A0;24)</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
